So
if we ask the concept of term insurance, many people do
not know what is the concept of term insurance
?  It is a pure life insurance.
You are getting your life covered.  You have
income replacement.  If you
are not with Lets, then how will your family's financial
goals be achieved?  That will be
from the term insurance policy.  So pure
term life policy is called term insurance.
And if you are looking to buy term insurance, then
this video
will be very helpful because we are comparing five such term
insurance plans of
2025 which will help you in knowing
which plans are suitable for you.  So all these
details have been taken from the IIDA report.  The
IID website has an annual report
and an insurance handbook.
This data has been taken from there.  So that you can
decide which policy is suitable for you.
[Music]
Moving on to the video, the five plans we are
comparing are LIC New Jiv
Number, ICICI Pension Protect Smart Plus,
Axis Max L Smart Term Plus, HDFC Life
Credit to Protect Super and Tata iHai
Insurance Sampoorna Raksha Plan.  So
we will compare these five plans.  But
before that we will compare these five companies
on different parameters.  So let us first
talk about
when the company Inception actually came into existence?  When did the company start?
As you know about LIC, LIC was started in 1956,
ICICI Principal in 2001,
Axis Max Life is now there.  Earlier it
was Max Life, only HDFC Life was started in 2000, Tata
IIA was started in 2000.  Now
here we will tell you some important
parameters on which you will
compare these companies before taking a term insurance policy.
So first we will look at the
claim settlement ratio.  Claim settlement
ratio means how many claims came, how many
claims were paid, that is the
claim settlement ratio of the company.  To calculate that,
we will have to see how many
claims came and how many were settled.  So
if we talk about the number of claims of LIC, then 844312
claims came out of which 829000 were
paid.  Their claim settlement ratio will be
98.22%.
ICICI Prudential received 13523 claims.
This is the data of 202324.  So, in 2324, so many
claims came.  13523
claims were received and 1341 were settled.  Claim
settlement ratio has come to 99.17%.
In Axis Max L, 19638 claims were received and 19569 were
settled, hence the claim settlement ratio is 99.64%.
HDFC L received 19432 claims and
settled on 19338, which means the claim settlement ratio
will be 99.51%.
Tata AI received 6431 claims in the year and
settled on 6375.  So 99.12% is the claim
settlement ratio for Tata AIA.  This is a
parameter called claim settlement ratio.   The
second parameter is Amount Settled
Ratio. What is Amount Settled Ratio
?  Meaning, how much amount was claimed and
how much amount was settled.  So the amount of
death claims paid
by LIC in 2024 is Rs 17,862 crore.
17,862
crores were paid.  The amount settlement ratio
is 95.18%,
which means that out of the amount filed, Rs
17862 was
paid. So, 95.18% is the amount
settlement ratio for LIC. Similarly,
in ICICI Protect, if you look at it, Rs 1866 is the amount
paid in death claims.  So the amount settlement
ratio becomes 98.75%.
You can see the same in HDFC Life.  Similarly, if you
look at Axis Max Ltd, Rs 1254 crore was paid
in death claims and the
amount settlement ratio is 97.10%.
In HDFC Ltd, Rs 1584
crore was paid in death claims.  95.70 is the amount
settlement ratio.  A claim of Rs 1086 crore was paid in Tata IA.
So ₹96.02%
is the amount settlement ratio.  Now let's talk about
solvency ratio.  Solvency
ratio is declared quarterly
on the IIDA website.  It tells us how solvent the
company is.  So
if we look at the solvency ratio of LIC, it is 1.98,
ICICI PDL is 1.92, Axis Max Life is
1.72, HDFC L is 1.87 and Tata II L is
1.75.  Now let us talk about
how much premium these companies
underwrote.  How much premium did they issue
last year in 2324?  LIC
did Rs 4,75,751
crore.  ICICI invested Rs 43,235
crore.  Axis Max Life invested Rs 29,528
crore.  HDFC L raised Rs 6376 crore and Tata
AIA raised Rs 25,691
crore.  So this is the total premium underwritten by
these companies last year.  Now let's talk about
assets under management.  What were its
assets under management as on March 31,
2024?  So the reports that come from IADA are
generally one year old reports.
So the reports that came in December
last year were of 232 reports.
What will come in December 2025 will be all the reports of 2425.
So new videos
will be made on that.  But now for old videos we
can refer the old data.  The assets
under management of LIC is Rs 44,23,579
crore.  ICICI has assets under management of Rs
286,000 crore.  Axis Max Life's ₹147,000
crore.  HDFC L has 287000 crores and Tata AI has
crores. This is the total assets under management as
on 31st March 2020. Now we will compare
their products. The names of the products are LIC
New Jiv, ICICI PNL iProtect Smart
Plus, Axis Max Life Smart Term Plus,
HDFC Click to Protect Super and Tata
AI Life Insurance Sampoorna Raksha.
We will compare these plans on different
parameters.  So first let us talk about
what minimum sum assured is available in these plans.
LIC New Jeevan Amar has a minimum
sum assured of Rs 25 lakh.  Minimum sum assured available is Rs. 50 lakh in ICICI Bank, Rs.
25 lakh in Axis Bank Max, Rs. 50 lakh in HDFC Life and Rs.
50 lakh in Tata Life.
Now what are sum assured options
?  Sum assured options mean
that your sum assured will remain the same throughout or keep
increasing.  Level sum assured.  If the sum
assured remains the same.  If your sum assured keeps
increasing then it is called Increasing Sum Assured
Option.  So if you look at the sum assured
option,
level sum assured is also available in LIC New Jeevan Amar.  This means you
have the option to keep your sum assured the same throughout.
You can have the same sum assured every year
or you can have the option of increasing sum
assured which will keep increasing by 10% every year with
inflation.
Level Sum Assured option is available in ICICI PDL iProtect Smart Plus.
Your level is also available in Axis Max L
and there is also an increasing sum assured option.
Level Sum Assured is available in HDFC L Click to Protect Super.
Your Level Sum Assured is available at Tata A Sampoorna Raksha.
If we talk about the policy term,
for how much term can you take the policy?
In LIC, you can take a policy term of minimum 10 years and maximum 40 years.
Meaning, at whatever age you are entering the policy, you can
take a policy for a minimum of 10 years and a maximum of 40 years.  ICICI Pens have a
minimum tenure of five years, maximum tenure of 40 years and
whole life option.  By whole life, I mean,
those plans cover you for 100 years.
Axis Max Life offers tenures ranging from 10 years to
67 years and
whole life option is also available.  Policy terms ranging
from five years to 40 years are
available at HDFC Life.  Plus whole life
option is also available.  Tata AIA offers tenure
options ranging from 10 years to 67 years
and whole life coverage is also available.
Premium paying term means
how can you pay your premium?   The
premium paying term is regular.   There is
limited payment.  Regular means
that you are paying the premium for the number of years the policy is in force.
Limited means
that your policy term is something else.
But your premium paying term is lower than the
policy term or single premium.  You can
finish it by paying the premium in one go.
So that will keep your cover going.
Whatever policy term you have taken, the premium will be paid only once.
So here in LIC, the
policy term is 5 years less and 10 years less in Regular Limited and single
premium option is available.  All
three options – Regular, Limited and Single –
are available in ICICI Ptial.  All
are available in Axis Max Life.  All three, Regular Limited Single are available in HDFC also.
And in Tata AI also
all three options Regular Single Limited
are available.  Now let's talk about the premium
payment mode.  So how
can you pay the premium?  If it is single premium
then it will go to One Go only.  But if regular or
limited premium payment option is taken then
how will it go?  So in that case, yearly and half
yearly options are available in LIC.
Yearly, half yearly and monthly options are available in ICICI PNL.
Meaning you can pay yearly
or half yearly or monthly.   It is done
on monthly ECS mode.  All four options –
Yearly, Half Yearly, Quarterly, Monthly –
are available in Axis Max L.
Yearly, Half Yearly, Quarterly, Monthly all
four options are available in HDFC L.  In Tata AIA,
choose yearly, half yearly, quarterly, monthly whichever you find convenient.  But if
you ask my opinion, according to me, term
insurance policy should not be taken on monthly basis.  Because
what happens monthly is auto
debit ECS.  If due to any
reason your monthly auto debit is not done then
your policy will lapse and you will
also come to know about it after two-three months, then it gets
challenged and the policy gets lapsed.
And you know that it is
very difficult to revive term insurance.  Now let's
talk about the minimum and maximum
entry age.  So minimum entry age like
adult can take this policy.  Because
you can take this policy when you start earning.  The
minimum entry age is 18 years.
Maximum 65 years in all the five policies.
Inbuilt benefits.  There will be some benefits
which are inbuilt in your plan and some are add
ons which you can add as riders.
Like your death benefit
is included inbuilt in LIC.  If death occurs, the sum
assured will be paid.  There are
three benefits included in ICICI Prudential.  There
is a waiver of premium if the death benefit is paid or if permanent disability and terminal illness occurs.  Waiver of premium and
early pay out in case of terminal illness.  The
sum assured is paid to you.
Terminal illness is basically that
illness where the doctor gives a time limit
that you have three months left, you have
six months left.  It is absolutely a terminal
illness.  If there is an end then your early
payout happens there.  The policy payout is the
death benefit you were supposed to
receive.  Death benefit is included in Axis Max L.  It
is inbuilt.
Death benefit is inbuilt in HDFC L and
death benefit is also inbuilt in Tata AI.  Optional riders
are available which you can add on
by paying additional premium.  So
your Accidental Death Benefit Rider
is available in LIC.  You can add that by
paying additional premium.
You can avail Accidental Death Benefit in ICICI PNL iProtect Smart Plus.
Secondly, you can add a critical illness rider
that is critical illness
accidental death benefit. As you understand,
you have taken an accidental rider on top of the death benefit you have received and you will
get more sum assured if the death occurs
through an accident. If you choose this rider,
your sum assured increases.  Critical
Illness basically means that if someone gets a critical
illness then the lump sum is paid out.
Lumsum pay out on diagnosis of critical
illness.  Every
company has a specified list of this.  The list of riders they provide is
these 30 diseases, these
40 diseases and so on and here the minimum
survival period is that one has to survive for 30 days
if one wants to take payout for critical illness, then
if we talk about Axis Max Life then there are four riders
available, one is Accidental Death Benefit
where your sum assured gets enhanced
in case of accidental death, second is
Critical Illness, here also the minimum survival period is
30 days.  The third is return
of premium, if you want your
premium to be returned, that is, the amount of
premium you have paid should be returned to you on maturity, then
that option is also available.
Fourth is waiver of premium.  If there is any
permanent disability or terminal illness, the
premium will be waived off.
HDFC L Crico Protect Super offers
accidental death benefit.  Then there is
Critical Illness Benefit, Return of
Premium, Waiver of Premium and Critical
Illness.  This rider is available that if a critical
illness is diagnosed, the premium will be waived off.  There are
five riders available in the Tata AIA Tata A Sampoorna Raksha plan.  The first
is accidental death benefit.  Then
Accidental Total and Permanent Disability
Benefit.  This is a separate rider.  Critical
Plus benefit where the minimum survival
period is again 30 days.  Return of
premium.  You want your premium to be
returned if death does not occur
within the defined term.  Then fifth is waiver of
premium in case of permanent disability.
In case of permanent disability, the premium will be waived off.
Now let's talk about the death benefit payout
option.  How will the death benefit be
received?  So the death benefit can be received lump sum or
one time.  Suppose there is an insurance of Rs 50 lakh, then the
nominee and the beneficiary
get Rs 50 lakh one time.  And the second option is
that you
create income.  If you feel that your
nominee will not be able to handle the lump sum,
then you can create an income.  The income can be stable income
, increasing income
or you can take a combination of lump sum and income.
This option is also available.  For example,
in LIC only lump sum option is available that only
lump sum will be given on death.  You have options available in ICICI PDL.
This option
is available to the policy holder.
Which option do they choose when they are buying a policy
?  That could be lumpsum, that could be
income.  That could be increasing income.
Income kept increasing every year.  The premium is
decided accordingly.  Or it could be that he
gave some lump sum and some income.  So lumpsum
and income.  So
your premium is decided according to the option you select.
Then there is Axis Max Lef in
both Lumpsum and Lumpsum & Income options.
Both Lumsum and Lumsum & Income options are available in HDFC L.
Lumpsum Lumpsum and Income and Enhance Sum
Assured in Tata IG.  So all these options are available which
you can choose while taking the policy.
Accordingly the premium
is decided.  Which death benefit payout option have you
chosen?  Next is pre policy
medical checkup.  When you take a policy, will there be a
medical test before taking the policy or
not?  Again it depends on the sum
assured.  What are you choosing Sum Assured
?  It will depend on your occupation.  It will depend on the
company you work for
and also on your age.
If one is young, many people do not even
ask for a turn.  It actually depends on
where you are working.  Sara is a combination of these things.
So it will depend on that basis whether there will be a
pre-policy medical checkup
or not.  But in 90% of the cases, there is a pre-
policy medical checkup, tests and
physical tests.  The
policy is given on that basis only.  Now I have done
some premium calculations for you here at Pay End.
So the premium as
you know the premium of term insurance
, smoker premium is different,
non smoker premium is different, male
premium is different and female premium
is different.  So I am sharing all the combinations with you
here.  And many companies
give discount to salaried people in the first year.
If you are salaried then
your premium will be less in the first year.  Next year
onwards the proper premium will go up.  Full
premium will be paid.  So here I have
taken all the combinations like salary, self employed etc.  Let us take a look at what the premiums are.
So if we talk about LIC,
we have taken a term of 39 years.
We have attained the age of 31 years.  The age of those taking the policy is
31 and 39 years.  Meaning the cover will be
till 70.  So you can see according to yourself
whether it is suitable for you or
not.  So, as I have taken in the case of salaried person, the
non-smoker premium in LIC is Rs 1718,
if you are a smoker then your premium is Rs
25205.  Non-smoker premium in ICICI Piden
is ₹84.  This includes GST and
smoker's premium is ₹14354.  In Axis Max Life, the
non-smoker premium is Rs 9274 and the
smoker premium is Rs 16692.
Smoker Premium in HDFC L is Rs 24151.  Non
smoker premium is 1275 in Tata AIA
10,000 and 16,000 smoker non smoker and
smoker premium now I have
taken smoker and non smoker premium for female also the
premium of female is less than male so
non smoker premium of female is 14000 and
smoker is 20000 similarly in ICICI 7100
and 12,000 in Axis Max L 7800 and 14000
in HDFC L 10000 and 20000 and in Tata AI
87 and 14000 now here I
told you that these are the premiums for salaried.
If you are salaried and working, then
this is the premium accordingly.  If you
are self-employed, your premiums may be different
for the first year.  From the second year
onwards, the full premium will be charged but a
discount is given on the first year which is
generally 15%.  So if you look here, the
premium in LIC is the same.  Whether you are salaried
or self-employed, your premium will remain the same.
But in ICICI pudential, if we
are self-employed, then in the first year our
premium as a male non-smoker will be Rs 9650,
male smoker Rs 16000, female non-smoker Rs 8200,
female smoker Rs 13000, similarly
you can see the rest of the premiums
on the screen in front of you.  So male female premium
is different.  Smoker and non-smoker are different.  Now
here the question arises that smoker or non
smoker is your lifestyle habit.  So
lifestyle habits should be told.  What
should be done?  Absolutely should be told.
We have also made a detailed video on this that
what challenge arises if you do not tell?  So you
can refer to that video if this is
your question.  So this premium
is the standard premium.  This is if there is no medical
condition.  You are absolutely healthy.
Your BAMI is fine.  You neither have BP nor
diabetes nor any pre-existing condition.
Neither is it your occupational hazard.  The place where you
work is also a completely safe place.
So this depends on that and your pin code.
Meaning, if everything is absolutely safe then
this is our premium.  If there is some deviation,
loading may be applied.  Premiums may increase.
Again it depends on the underwriting
team.  Now for term insurance, we know
that there is medical underwriting as
we discussed and there is also financial underwriting as to
what is your maximum eligibility to take the policy.  You
can take the policy accordingly and take that much in total.
Suppose your eligibility is Rs 1
crore on this basis.  So in total
you can take a policy of Rs 1 crore.  You
cannot take Rs 1 crore each from two companies as per your
financial eligibility.  So
both are underwritten.  Financial
underwriting and medical underwriting.  And more
details as I told you there is the ultimate
term insurance checklist.  You
can see the details there.  If
you want to take term insurance, then if you refer to these two videos,
I am sure you will get a
good term insurance policy
and will be able to fully secure your family.
So this was my pick of the
best term insurance plans that are
available in India in 2025.  There will be questions.
Please reach out below
in the comments section.  You can reach out to our team.
And tell me on what we should make the next video.
Quick reminder before you go
if you haven't subscribed to our channel.
So that you
get the right infection at the right time.  And
please share this video with your friends
who are still looking for term insurance
and have not bought a good term insurance
policy.  See you
in the next video.  Till then stay safe.  Take
care.  Bye-bye.
Om